Alright, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today’s דף daf is קי, kuf yud,
110, and we pick up in the middle of קט עמוד ב
kuf tes amud bais which we fell a little behind, but this
גמרא Gemara should go pretty quickly.
And it says like this, תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: לה' לכהן. L'Hashem
l'Kohen. It’s about fifteen lines down from the top of קט עמוד
ב, kuf tes amud bais, starts with a quote of the פסוק:
pasuk: לה' לכהן. L'Hashem l'Kohen. So this is the מצווה mitzvah of
if somebody swears again, once again, strange these גמרות Gemarot because there’s
like long גמרא Gemara discussions about a משנה Mishnah that really relates
to the משנה Mishnah that’s about to come up. So much of
the discussion is about somebody who swears falsely and he pays קרן
וחומש keren v'chomesh or he pays כפל kefel if it’s a claim
of גניבה, geneivah,
you know, we did before the משנה. Mishnah.
Now we're doing the discussion of גזל הגר, gezel hager, which is
really what’s going to be coming up in the coming משנה. Mishnah.
So first we had a discussion yesterday, the little top of this
עמוד ב, amud bais, about what happens if it's somebody steals from
a גיורת. giyoret. You know, the תורה Torah says איש, ish, so
we say איש ish doesn't mean specifically איש ish and includes even
אשה, ishah, and therefore you would have—is that me? Yes, it is
me. I'm telling you all the class is starting. No, this thing,
I don’t know what my phone does sometimes. Exactly. Anyway, and that
the same הלכה halacha applies if somebody swears falsely, normally you would
give the principle and a חומש chomesh and an אשם, asham, but
if it’s a גר ger who dies and there is no relatives,
so that you give it to the—you bring it to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you give the principle and the חומש chomesh
to the כוהנים. Kohanim. So now we’re continuing with that discussion of
גזל הגר. gezel hager. So, here we go.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: לה' לכהן. L'Hashem l'Kohen. קנאו ה', Kina'o Hashem,
so what does it mean לה' L'Hashem to the כהן? Kohen? Which
one is it? God has acquired it ונתנו לכהן, u'netano l'Kohen, and
He gives it to the כהן. Kohen. So it's sort of like
it’s first, as it were, given as an offering to God, which
makes it a type of an act of כפרה kaparah or an
act of a קרבן, korban, and then God awards it to the
כהן. Kohen. Sort of like when you bring a חטאת, chatas, you
bring it to God and then the כוהנים Kohanim eat from the
meat. Okay, so it’s a similar type of an idea. שבאותו משמר.
She'b'oso mishmar. Now we’re adding to that the idea that which כהן
Kohen gets it? The כהן Kohen that happens to be working in
that משמר, mishmar, in that week in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
They would have—they would alternate weeks. So it’s the כוהנים Kohanim that
are working in that week, they split it. It’s interesting it doesn’t
say בית אב, Beis Av, that day. Right, so at least so
somehow
because—but the primary division of כוהנים Kohanim is between the משמרות, mishmaros,
weeks, and therefore we understand that it's shared equally by all of
them. אתו אומר לכהן שבאותו משמר, Atu omer l'Kohen she'b'oso mishmar, you
say it’s given just to that משמר. mishmar. או לכל כהן שירצה,
O l'chol Kohen she'yirtzeh, maybe you get to decide which כהן Kohen
to give it to. You know, give it to a particular כהן.
Kohen. And maybe even more than that, right, maybe it’s not even
one that’s working that week at all. כשהוא אומר, K'shehu omer, when
the פסוק pasuk says מלבד איל הכיפורים אשר יכפר בו עליו, milvad
eil hakippurim asher yechaper bo alav,
it says that you return this אשם asham which here this אשם
asham is meant not as the קרבן אשם, korban asham, but we’re
going to say in a minute this word אשם asham here means
the principle, the money. So it says you give it in addition
to the ram of atonement. That is the אשם קרבן. asham korban.
So now who gets the ram of atonement? Who shares in the
קרבנות korbanos that are brought?
The ones that day though?
Well, that is true. I mean practically it's the ones that day.
Yeah, I don't know exactly how to answer—that’s a good point, but
okay, but the same way the קרבן korban is shared by the
כוהנים Kohanim who are working then, so similarly this is shared. Michael
asks of course an excellent question that again why are we focusing
on that week as opposed to
that
day? Okay, so תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הרי שהיה גוזל כהן. Harei
she'hayah gozel Kohen.
Let’s say the one who stole from the גר ger was a
כהן. Kohen. And then it came his time to give it back.
So, and he wisely chose to bring back the קרבן korban and
to bring the principle back on the week that he's going up
to ירושלים Yerushalayim anyway and on his week that he was serving
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So he’s going to say the
following: מנין שלא יאמר, Minayin she'lo yomar, how do we know he
shouldn’t say, listen, הואיל ויוצא לכוהנים, hovil v'yotzei l'Kohanim,
since it’s anyway going to be given out to the כוהנים Kohanim
that are working this
week, והרי תחת ידי, v'harei tachas yadi, and I’m holding onto it
anyway, יהא שלי, yehei sheli, let me keep it. Now of course
the interesting thing is that you could have asked the question from
yesterday, which is that even if from a דיני ממונות dinei mamonus
maybe he has a right to keep it, the מצווה mitzvah of
השבה hashavah should require an act of giving it back. And interestingly
the גמרא Gemara does not answer on that basis. It really could
have answered totally on the basis of what we said on עמוד
א, amud aleph, that the monetary issue isn’t sufficient, there needs to
be an act of returning it. But anyway, let’s see what the
גמרא Gemara does answer. How do we know he’s not allowed to
say that? ודין הוא, V'din hu, and you could argue this logically.
אם בשל אחרים הוא זוכה, Im b'shel acherim hu zocheh, look,
if some other stranger would come and bring the גזל הגר, gezel
hager, I'd have a portion to it. בשל עצמו לא כל שכן,
B'shel atzmo lo kol shekein, how much more so should I have
a portion in the one that I myself am bringing and I
already have it in my pocket? Of course that’s a limited קל
וחומר kal v'chomer because then okay fine you can keep your portion,
but you know you’d— but every all the other כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*
have to share equally, that doesn't prove you get to keep the
whole thing in your pocket. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
so therefore that's why רבי נתן *Rebbi Nason* says it in a
slightly different version. רבי נתן אומר בלשון אחר *Rebbi Nason omeir belashon
acher*, רבי נתן *Rebbi Nason* says the whole argument could be made
in the following way, slightly different version. ומה דבר שאין לו חלק
בו עד שיכנס ברשותו *U-mah davar she-ein lo chelek bo ad sheyikanes
birshuto*, look, something that I've no rights to until it's given over,
until somebody gives it, כשיכנס ברשותו *kesheyikanes birshuto* once it gets under
my control, אינו יכול להוציא מידו *eino yachol lehotzi miyado*, I don't
have to, nobody else has rights to it, which is what? So
like anything that כהנים Kohanim? *kohanim* are given, תרומה *trumah*, ביכורים *bikkurim*,
but let's take תרומה *trumah*, okay? You have a right, Michael here
has a right to give תרומה *trumah* to whoever he wants. I'm
a כהן Kohen *kohein*. Before he gave it to me, I had
absolutely no rights to it. I had no claim on it. Once
he gives it to me, once it's under my
control, it's all mine, no other כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* have a right
to it. So if that's true about something that started out that
I had no rights to it once it's under my control I
have full rights to it, so if that's true, דבר שיש לו
חלק בו davar she-yesh lo chelek bo *davar she-yesh lo chelek bo*,
this money that I have to that I stole that I start
by I do have a right to it because
a portion of it is going to be mine even if I
give it back to the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* I'm going to in
the end get a portion. So something that I start with a
rightful claim on it, עד שלא יכנס ברשותו *ad she-lo
yikanes birshuto*, even before it would be essentially something that would come
under my control, right? If some stranger would bring out during my
week גזל הגר gezel hager. *gezel hager*, I would have a right
to it. Okay, if somebody's looking for which כהן Kohen *kohein* to
give תרומה *trumah* to, I have no particular claim. But when he
chooses to give it to me, it's all mine. So this week
that I'm working in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* if
some stranger were to bring גזל הגר gezel hager, *gezel hager*, I'd
have a claim to it. So therefore now that it's under my
control, my own גזל הגר gezel hager, *gezel hager*, it should all
be mine. Okay,
so דבר שיש לו חלק בו עד שלא נכנס ברשותו אינו דין
דאינו יכול להוציא מידו *davar she-yesh lo chelek bo ad she-lo nichnas
lirishuto eino din de-eino yachol lehotzi miyado*? So that's the קל וחומר
kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*. Okay, now that it's under my control and
since I should have total, nobody else should have rights to it.
It says no, that's what it says the problem with that קל
וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*. לא *Lo*. אם אמרת בדבר שאין לו
חלק בו *Im amarta bidavar she-ein lo chelek bo* if it's something
like תרומה *trumah* שכשם שאין לו חלק בו *she-kesheim she-ein lo chelek
bo*, Michael's looking around which כהן Kohen *kohein* to give the תרומה
*trumah* to, I have no particular claim to it, but כך אין
לאחרים חלק בו *kach ein leachairim chelek bo*. Nobody no other כהנים
Kohanim. *kohanim* have a claim to it. So if he gives it
to me, it's all mine. תאמר בגזל *Tomer bagezel*, but now it's
my week in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and somebody
is coming to give גזל הגר gezel hager, *gezel hager*, שכשם שיש
לו חלק בו *she-kesheim she-yesh lo chelek bo*,
a גזל הגר gezel hager. *gezel hager* that's going to be given
back this week, yes it's true I have a claim to it,
but כך יש לאחרים חלק בו *kach yesh leachairim chelek bo*. All
the other כהנים kohanim *kohanim* working this week have a claim to
it. So if that's true, just because it's under my, just because
it's in my pocket right now doesn't mean it's all mine because
everybody else started with a claim to it. Okay, אלא ela פוך
*Ella puch*, this קל וחומר *kal vachomer* you want to make is
not a legitimate one, there's no argument to say that you should
be able to hold on to more than is your portion. גזלה
יוצאה מתחת ידו *Gezeilah yotzei-ah mitachat yado*, this גזלה *gezeilah* you bring
you have to give it up even if it's yours and it's
your day of working in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*,
ומתחלק לכל אחיו הכהנים *umitchalek lechol echav hakohanim*, and it's divided to
all other the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. Now, והכתיב *Ve-haktiv*,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay we get that the קל
וחומר *kal vachomer* didn't work, thank you so much. והכתיב *Ve-haktiv* but
doesn't the verse say,
where are we? והכתיב ואיש את קדשיו לו יהיו v’ish et kodashav
lo yihyu. *Ve-haktiv ve-ish et kodashav lo yihyu*. We're going to learn
in a minute, we're really going to digress, we're going to learn
an idea that a כהן Kohen, *kohein* who comes any day to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, it's not my week to
do the עבודה avoda, *avodah* in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis
HaMikdash*, but I'm bringing a קרבן korban *korban* today, my own personal
קרבן korban *korban*. When I bring a קרבן korban, *korban* any day
during the year, I have a right to do the עבודה avoda,
*avodah* on my own קרבן korban *korban*. Okay, and we learn that
from the פסוק pasuk. ואיש את קדשיו לו יהיו *pasuk ve-ish et
kodashav lo yihyu*. Each man can have his own sacrifices, which we
understand to be any כהן Kohen *kohein* who comes gets the right
to bring his own קרבן korban. *korban*. So here I am, I'm
returning, I'm bringing my אשם asham *asham* for my גזל הגר gezel
hager *gezel hager*. I have the right to be מקריב makriv *makriv*
the אשם asham *asham*. All right, I'm מקריב makriv *makriv* the אשם
asham *asham* but now that's very interesting because the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says האשם ha-asham, המושב להשם לכהן L'Hashem L'Kohein. *ha-asham hamushav la'Hashem lakohein*,
the principal goes back to the כהן Kohen, *kohein*, מלבד איל הכפורים
Milvad eil hakippurim *mimalvad eil hachippurim*, in addition to the קרבן אשם
Korban asham. *korban asham*. And from that we learned that the same
way all the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* share in the קרבן korban. אשם
asham *korban asham*, all the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* share in the גזל
הגר gezel hager *gezel hager*. But if I'm bringing the קרבן korban.
*korban*, I get a right to bring it and I get a
right to have the meat of the קרבן korban, *korban*. So if
I have a right to eat the meat alone of my קרבן
korban אשם asham, *korban asham*, I should get a right to keep
the money because we learned that the money is distributed the same
way the קרבן korban *korban* is distributed. Okay, so that's a much
better argument. All right.
So ואיש את קדשיו לו יהיו *ve-ish et kodashav lo yihyu* this
applies to the כהן Kohen *kohein*, I thought it meant that a
person who brings it can give it to any כהן Kohen. *kohein*.
No, at least according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* on the תורה Torah
*Torah*.
Well, no that's not true. Okay. המשיא אמר מתנות כהונה matnot kehuna.
ולוויה יכול יבא ויתן לידי זרע עצמו תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ואיש
את קדשיו לו יהיו *Ha-meshia amar matnos kehunah u-leviyah yachol yavo ve-yitein
liyadei zera atzmo talmud lomar ve-ish et kodashav lo yihyu* it should
be... מה מצינו שמנע ממתנות כהונה ולווייה יכול יבואו ויטלו לעצמם תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar, איש אשר לו יהיו הקישו הכתוב לתרומה שניתנה במתנה.
What?
Anyway,
yes,
that just means that that's מתנות כהונה. That's תרומה ומעשר, truma u'ma'aser,
that's not קרבנות. korbanot.
Yeah, but that's what I'm saying, it's on that פסוק.
pasuk Yeah, I know, but that's not the only דרשה.
derasha. Somebody who was stole and returned it and is now bringing
the אשם asham and has the money for the גר. ger.
Exactly. So the question is, so who does the money go to?
He wants to keep the money. So what we're saying is you
can't make a logical argument you keep the money, but because we
know that a כהן Kohen. who brings a קרבן korban has a
right to bring the קרבן korban and have the meat of that
קרבן, korban, and since the פסוק pasuk that tells us that the
money of the גר ger goes to who the קרבן korban, goes,
which usually means all the כהנים, Kohanim but here it should mean
the guy
himself. Okay. והכתיב איש קדשיו לו יהיו. ve-haktiv ish kodashav lo yihyu.
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha be-mai askinan בכהן טמא. be-Kohen tamei. Ah, he's
טמא. tamei. Because he's טמא tamei he can't bring his own קרבן.
korban So therefore he can't keep the אשם asham money. That's really
stupid. Wait until you're not טמא tamei and then bring the קרבן.
korban, Okay.
Doesn't it say the same that you do get the קדשים kodashim
and then it talks about that you're טמא tamei then you can't
get your קדשים?
kodashim? No, no, הכא במאי עסקינן hacha be-mai askinan that the כהן
Kohen doesn't get to keep his own the money, the גזל הגר.
gezel hager Okay, of course the point the גמרא Gemara is doing
is it's conceding that if you were not טמא tamei you would
get to keep the גזל הגר, gezel hager. and it seems like
we're trying to argue that you never get to keep your own
גזל הגר, gezel hager, at least not exclusively. אי בכהן טמא i
be-Kohen tamei דבר שיש לו חלק בו מי אית ליה? mi it
lei? So אלא אתיא... ela atya...
okay,
so if that's if it's if it's case of a כהן טמא,
Kohen tamei, wait a minute, what's this question here? One minute.
He had an argument to begin with.
Yeah, then it sounds like you never had an argument to begin
with. One minute. היכא דאמר... hecha de-amar...
right, if it was the כהן טמא, Kohen tamei, how could he
have even started with his argument 'Oh, I have a right here'.
You do, you have a right to the money but you don't
have a right to the קרבן. korban? Anyway, fine. But the גמרא
Gemara says, but basically the point is it sounds like we're trying
to make an argument that he never gets to keep his גזל
הגר, gezel hager, not just in a case when he's טמא. tamei.
אלא ela, says the גמרא Gemara you're right. Actually, based on the
פסוק pasuk of having a right to the קרבן, korban you would
have logically argued he does have a right to the גזל הגר.
gezel hager, אלא, but here's how we know he doesn't. אתיא לכהן
לכהן משדה אחוזה. atya lachohen lachohen misdei achuza.
It's the גזרה שוה gezera shava from something else that goes to
a כהן Kohen that we know he doesn't get to keep to
himself. Here it says האשם, the אשם asham. in this פסוק pasuk?
means the principal, is לה' לכהן, la-Hashem la-Kohen, and we have another
פסוק posuk that says something goes to the כהן, kohen, the שדה
אחוזה. sdeh achuza. What's שדה אחוזה? sdeh achuza? I sanctified my field
of inheritance, I'm able to redeem it. If I don't redeem it,
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash sells it and takes the money. And
then when the, when what do you call it, when the יובל
Yovel rolls around,
then everybody that the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, sold these sanctified fields
to, leaves their hands but it doesn't go back to the original
owners, it goes back to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. benefits doubly from this. Okay, now who gets
to keep it? It says לכהנים. lakohanim. Which כהנים? Kohanim So the
כהנים Kohanim that are working during that week that the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur of the יובל Yovel falls out. Yeah, exactly, imagine that.
Anyway, לכהן משדה אחוזה. lachohen misdei achuza. דתניא, detanya, אחוזתו. achuzato. So
it says his אחוזה. achuza. משדה אחוזתו. misdei achuzato. מה תלמוד לומר
ma talmud lomar אחוזתו? achuzato? מנין לשדה היוצא לכהנים ביובל וגאלה אחד
מן הכהנים? minayin lesadeh hayotzei lakohanim ba-yovel vegalla echad min hakohanim? So
here we've got a field that somebody sanctified and I'm a כהן
kohen and I redeemed it for myself. לכהן
תהיה אחוזתו. lachohen tihyeh achuzato. It just could have said לכהן תהיה.
lachohen tihyeh. Your inheritance goes to the כהן, kohen why does it
say אחוזתו? achuzato? מה תלמוד לומר? ma talmud lomar? מנין לשדה היוצא
לכהנים ביובל minayin lesadeh hayotzei lakohanim ba-yovel וגאלה אחד מן הכהנים? vegalla
echad min hakohanim? So here we've got a field that somebody sanctified
and I'm a כהן kohen and I redeemed it for myself. And
now it's my week is going to fall out during the week
that all the fields go back. So that's not enough that I'm
going to get the enormous windfall, I want to keep to myself
this field that it's now under my control. I bought this field
from the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash okay? Rather than it go back
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and being distributed equally, I want
to keep it all to myself. A very similar type of an
idea. It's already under my control. מנין שלא יאמר minayin shelo yomar
הואיל ויוצא לכהנים ביובל, ho'il ve-yotzei lakohanim ba-yovel, since anyway you're going
to go to כהנים Kohanim, and be divided, והרי היא תחת ידי
ve-harei hi tachat yadi it's already under my control, תהא שלי, tehe
sheli, let me just keep it, I'm going to keep it fully.
ודין הוא, vedin hu, and I can make a קל וחומר. It
sounds like very much what we said before. בשל אחרים אני זוכה,
beshel acherim ani zocheh, if I'm going to get other people's fields,
בשל עצמי לא כל שכן, beshel atzmi lo kol sheken, how much
more so should I get mine? Of course it's not exactly קל
וחומר because here you want to get yours fully, not just keep
your portion. Anyway, תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, כשדה החרם לכהן kisdeh hacharem
lachohen, תהיה אחוזתו. achuzato, Like a field that has been under the
ban, anyway your inheritance should go to the כהן. kohen
אחוזה שלו ואין זו שלו. achuza shelo ve-ein zu shelo. Okay, so
how are we reading it in? I hold on, אחוזתו, achuzato! your
inheritance,
it's yours but it's not yours.
Yeah,
so כשדה החרם kisdeh hacharem לכהן,
לכהן תהיה, lachohen tihyeh, your inheritance should be to the כהן. Kohen
אחוזה שלו. achuza shelo. Oh, his אחוזה. achuza.
Oh, he links כהן Kohen to שדה. sadeh.
Oh, his אחוזתו! And this field is not the Cohen’s אחוזה. achuza.
I like that. But it doesn’t start right but not like it’s
right but not that it doesn’t become the Cohen’s אחוזה, achuza, I
think it also doesn’t start as the Cohen’s אחוזה, achuza, right? So
this field is not the Cohen’s אחוזה achuza that he gets the
rights to it exclusively. It gets divided equally. הכיצד? Hakeitzad? So it’s
not exclusively the Cohen’s. יוצא מתחת ידו מתחלק לכל הכהנים. Yotzei mitachat
yado mit’chalek l’chol ha-Kohanim.
So even though it’s under his control and he bought it from
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. when the יובל Yovel runs around, comes
around, it gets divided equally. And since that’s true by this, it’s
true by the גזל הגר gezel hager even though the גזל הגר
gezel hager? is linked to the קרבן korban, and the Cohen does
have a right to the קרבן korban he’s going to bring, and
you should say it’s a package, this teaches you that no, the
actual גזל הגר gezel hager, itself gets distributed equally.
I’m also curious as to how
חזל Chazal read those words.
לכהן תהיה אחוזתו, lachohen tihyeh achuzato. so אחוזה שלו, achuza shelo, and
אין כולו שלו. ein kulo shelo. In other words, the Cohen has
אחוזת, achuzat, has this אחוזה, achuza, has a
portion
in it but not the entirety of it.
Yeah, okay. Now that we have mentioned as a digression, again, first
of all, the whole discussion is a digression, but the whole discussion
belongs on the next משנה mishna because the next משנה mishna is
גזל הגר. gezel hager Very funny, the גמרא Gemara is always anticipating
the next משנה. mishna. But as a digression, we mentioned this idea
the Cohen has the right to bring a קרבן korban, whenever he
shows up and to, and to benefit from it and to be
the only one that sort of gets this, you know, the meat
and whatever. So now we’re going to discuss that הלכה. halacha. So
let’s take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Why, how,
why, okay, why is he is bringing this, this robbery, that’s to
do with כפרה, kapara, right? Yeah. So I mean at the same
time he wants to hold onto this thing he robbed while he’s
trying to get כפרה. kapara. Right. It’s like holding a שרץ sheretz
when you’re going to...
It’s a very good point, which is sort of the point I
was making, which is even if somehow we might have some monetary
claim to it, where’s that whole idea of yesterday that you have
to, we have to do some act of giving it back. Right.
It’s very funny the גמרא Gemara did not bring that up here.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. מנין? Minayin? מנין לכהן שבא מקריב קרבנותיו
בכל עת ובכל שעה
שירצה? Minayin l’Kohen she-ba makriv korbanotav b’chol eit u’v’chol sha’ah she-yirtzeh? How
do you know a Cohen can come and bring his קרבן korban
anytime he wants?
תלמוד לומר, right,
ובא בכל אות נפשו ושרת. u’va b’chol avat nafsho v’shiret.
So we’re going to get to other things that are not as
explicit.
Okay, he
comes to his desire and he serves. מנין שעבודתו ועורו שלו? Minayin
she-avodato v’oro shelo? This is what we are going to, this is
where we’re leading to, which is not as explicit. How do you
know that when he does that he’s allowed to keep the benefit
of the קרבן, Korban the meat and the, and the skin, the
leather? תלמוד לומר, ואיש את קדשיו לו יהיו. Okay, which is written
right, which is actually written in a different place. Okay, so a
person keeps his קדשים, kodashim, so here it’s read as if you
bring your own קרבן, Korban, you get to keep it. הכיצד? Hakeitzad?
Do they allow the same דרשה drasha from the same פסוק?
pasuk I thought they don’t like to do that. Yeah, oh we
mean in בבא קמא? Bava Kamma? I don’t know.
Sometimes we do when we want to. הכיצד? Hakeitzad? אם היה בעל
מום נותנה לכהן שבאותה משמר. Im haya ba’al mum notnah l’Kohen she-ba-otah
mishmar. Now here’s meaning הכיצד, Hakeitzad, the normal case הכיצד Hakeitzad is
obvious: you come you bring your קרבן Korban. you benefit from it.
Here the הכיצד Hakeitzad is going to say what about cases that
you can’t actually do both? And we’re going to talk about two
scenarios. One scenario where you can’t be מקריב makriv but you’re theoretically
possible for you to eat it, and the other is where you
can be מקריב makriv but you can’t eat it. Okay, if you
can do both, you bring it, you מקריב makriv. it and you
benefit, you get the meat. Okay, but what about a stranger case?
אם היה בעל מום, Im haya ba’al mum, you have, you are
Cohen with a בעל מום. ba’al mum. A כהן Kohen, with a
בעל מום ba’al mum is not allowed to, to do the עבודה,
avoda, but the Torah does say that he’s allowed to eat the
meat of the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so you’re bringing your קרבן, Korban.
you can’t do the עבודה, avoda. some other Cohen is going to
do your עבודה, avoda, are you still entitled to make full claim
over the meat of the
קרבן? Korban Yeah, obviously, so or any of it, but certainly all
of it is the point here. נותנה לכהן שבאותה משמר, Notnah l’Kohen
she-ba-otah mishmar, you give it to the Cohen there. Now part of
the point here is there’s another point which is besides your rights
to the meat you have a right to do the עבודה. avoda,
Can you assign that right to somebody else? So forget for a
moment who’s going to get the meat. Can I sort of say,
I want my pal here, Frank, to do the עבודה, avoda okay,
he just likes more opportunities to throw, forget who’s going to eat
the meat. Okay, since I have a right to do the עבודה,
avoda or do we say no, since you’re a בעל מום, ba’al
mum, you don’t have that right anymore and therefore you can’t assign
that right. So that’s the first point of this. נותנה לכהן שבאותה
משמר, Notnah l’Kohen she-ba-otah mishmar, you do not have a right to
assign which Cohen does it since you couldn’t do it yourself. Now
who eats the meat? So there it says ועבודתו ועורו שלו, v’avodato
v’oro shelo, the עבודה avoda here means the, the meat, the result
of the meat and the leather you get to keep yourself since
you are a, since you’re a בעל מום, ba’al mum, you’re entitled
to eat the meat even though you can’t do the עבודה avoda,
you get to keep it. Now Rashi actually has a different גרסא
girsa which says ועבודתו ועורו לאנשי משמר. v’avodato v’oro l’anshei mishmar. That
since your right to eat the meat sort of derived from your
right to do the עבודה avoda and you don’t have any more
right to do the עבודה, avodah, then it gets equally divided by
all the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, so two very different versions of this
ברייתא. braita. You certainly no longer have the right to do the
עבודה avodah. and therefore you can’t assign it. Are you able to
retain your right to for the meat independent of your right to
do the עבודה, avodah that's two different versions of this ברייתא. braita.
That's when you're not able to do the עבודה. avodah Now it
continues on the top of ק"י עמוד א', Kuf Yud amud aleph,
והיה אם היה זקן, v'haya im haya zaken, let's say you were
elderly, so you were able to do the עבודה avodah, but you
did not have the capacity to really eat, just physically you couldn't
really eat meat or couldn't eat much of it, well, okay, או
חולה o choleh or a sick person.
Can one person eat the whole thing? It's a whole animal.
Well, he could
be a super healthy guy. The whole animal?
Yeah, I mean it's a good question by a חטאת chatas because
a חטאת chatas you only have one day and you can't bring
it outside the environment of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash I mean
maybe you can have your other friends כהנים Kohanim, come and share
with you but you know it's for your discretion who you want
to invite to your barbecue, you know. Okay, so in that case
אם היה זקן או חולה im haya zaken o choleh which we
assume is sort of this category of able to do the עבודה
avodah, but not able to eat the meat, in that case נותן
לכל כהן שירצה, noten lechol kohen sheyirtzeh, so or maybe you're not
so prepared to do the עבודה, avodah you are also elderly, so
but because in theory you can do the עבודה, avodah you can
assign it to any כהן, Kohen you don't have to it doesn't
have to be random because you in theory could do it yourself
you still have the right to do it and you can assign
it to whichever כהן Kohen you want, ועבודה סברה לאנשי משמר, v'avodah
savrah l'anshei mishmar, but you have to the meat gets eaten equally
by everybody because presumably you're not capable of eating the meat yourself.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't understand why are we treating the ability
to do the עבודה avodah, different from your ability to do the
eat the meat, one minute, האי זקן או חולה היכי דמי, hai
zaken o choleh heichi dami, what's the case? אי דמטי עביד עבודה,
ei d'mati avid avodah, if you're still able to do the עבודה
avodah? even though you're sick or
elderly, עבודה סברה נמי כבידי דידיה, avodah savrah nami k'vidi didei,
so we should consider it like you're in a normal state and
you should have the right to assign it and you should have
the right to eat the meat. Okay, ואי דלא מטי עביד עבודה,
v'ei d'lo mati avid avodah,
and if you're so sick or elderly you can't do the עבודה,
Avodah, so שליחיה היכי משוי, shlichia heichi mashvi, how can you assign
who gets to do the עבודה? avodah, אז אמר רב פפא שיכול
לעשות על ידי הדחק. Az amar Rav Papa sheyachol la'asos al yedei
hadachak.
So you know it's hard for you, you're elderly, it's hard. עבודה,
avodah, so when it comes to doing the עבודה, avodah, דכי עביד
על ידי הדחק עבודה היא, d'chi avid al yedei hadachak avodah hi,
you know you manage to struggle through it you know and you
creak around a little bit, I just turned fifty so I understand
it, anyway, so alright so nevertheless if it even if it takes
you a little longer it's still an עבודה, avodah so you still
have the capacity to do the עבודה, avodah you could still assign
it. אבל אכילה, But achila, but when it comes to eating, דכי
אכיל על ידי הדחק אכילה גסה היא, d'chi achil al yedei hadachak
achila gassa hi, if you have to eat the meat you're really
going to be forcing yourself and even though in theory you could
swallow it but when you're forcing yourself to eat and you really
like don't want to be eating, הלכתית halachically that's not considered an
eating, אכילה גסה achila gassa isn't considered an eating. Now it's funny
the word גסה gassa because גסה gassa normally means like גסה gassa
it's fat, it's big, it's like you're stuffing yourself after you're full,
but it really can mean also just mean an eating that you
don't like your body is resisting, like you know it's like it's
hard to go down, so even if it's resisting because you know
not because you're fat because you don't have any appetite or whatever
it is. Alright and תוספות Tosefos also has a discussion, do we
always say that אכילה גסה achila gassa doesn't count as an eating?
Sometimes it seems like we say it does, so תוספות Tosefos made
the you know there's different degrees of גסה, gassa, there's like oh
no I'm so full, oh dessert, okay I've got room for dessert
or whatever it is, okay you know and then there's the time
where no it's really beyond like really forced yourself forcing yourself to
eat where it doesn't count. So whatever it is here the גמרא
Gemara says that because it's so hard for you the eating would
not really constitute an act of eating. So therefore
אכילה גסה לאו כלום הוא. achila gassa lav klum hu. משום הכי
עבודה סברה לאנשי משמר. Mishum hachi avodah savrah l'anshei mishmar. So therefore
I mean in a way it's just a way of saying you're
physically able to do the עבודה avodah but you're not able to
do the eating, so therefore you can assign the עבודה avodah. because
that in theory you could do yourself, the eating which you can't
do yourself you don't have a right to assign. The funny thing
though is that even though I've assigned the עבודה avodah to a
particular כהן Kohen and this כהן Kohen now has the right to
do it, you might want to think that he also has the
right to get the meat because the right of eating the meat
seems to derive from the right to do the עבודה. avodah But
we're seeing to say not that way, that they're separate rights, especially
if you have the גרסא girsa we had in the at the
you know at the first case, that even though I can't even
though I can't do the עבודה avodah and I can't assign the
עבודה avodah, I retain my right to eat, it's really saying those
are independent rights, they're not linked. So therefore in this case I
retain the right to assign it but that doesn't give that כהן
Kohen the meat, the right of the meat is an independent right,
that one since I'm not capable of doing that gets shared equally
by the כהנים Kohanim? of the משמר. mishmar. Yes, Michael question.
The one is when we say doing the עבודה avodah, what do
we mean? Does it just mean
the זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, right?
Well whichever part you want to do.
I mean assume it's a שחיטה, shechita, the קבלה, kabala, הולכה, holacha,
the זריקה, zrika, can you even do the שחיטה? shechita? Well if
you could do it all with your right hand it might be
a little bit of a trick to manage to do
all. No but meaning you've even have to
divide it by like four people or all that?
I assume you do.
Well I'll tell you what.
Normally, but not necessarily. And it's normally divided anyway, like by the
תמיד, Tamid, when they would do other קרבנות, korbanos, I think. I'm
not sure exactly how they would arrange it. But yeah.
The next question I had was really is all that has to
be halachically needed to be is a כזית kezayit and then the
rest of it is just sort of like icing on the cake?
No, you're thinking of like about the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, but
no, a קרבן Korban has to totally be eaten by the כהנים.
Kohanim. There's an איסור issur of leaving it over, of נותר, nosar,
whatever, you know. Now it's not a חיוב גברא chiyuv gavra to
eat. It's not like I must eat the קרבן, Korban it's a
חיוב חפצא, chiyuv cheftza, the קרבן korban, needs to be eaten by
the כהנים. Kohanim, Okay.
I was thinking like you know,
there's no way to anyway eat all the meat of the קרבן,
korban so.
Okay fine, but you get to decide who to invite to your
barbecue. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, אם היה כהן טמא
בקרבן ציבור. im haya Kohen tamei be-korban tzibbur. Now let's say you
are a כהן Kohen. and you're bringing a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur.
I have to tell you, I didn't do a lot of research,
but I wasn't able immediately to find anybody to discuss this. What
the heck does that mean you're bringing a קרבן ציבור? korban tzibbur?
A קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur is brought by communal funds. Since when
are you bringing a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur to be brought? Maybe
it means you donated your sheep to the ציבור tzibbur and because
you know, you made it a gift of the... not exactly sure
what the scenario is that you're bringing a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur.
Okay. What?
No, no, no, it's just going to ask how, what's the scenario
that a טמא tamei person, you'll see what the גמרא Gemara asks.
I'm asking the question about what's the scenario that you are bringing
your קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. Oh, so I thought we were
talking in general about a טמא tamei who brings a קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibbur.
No,
no, no, not that's מקריב makriv the קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. You
brought a, it's, we're still talking about the scenario that you're coming
on a day that's not yours with a קרבן korban, and you
want the right to be מקריב. makriv, Okay. But what does it
mean that you're coming and offering to us a קרבן ציבור korban
tzibbur to be brought? Like קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur are things we
buy with communal funds. All right, so I don't really get
this רישא, reisha, אם היה הכהן טמא במשמר שזכה בקרבן ציבור להקריב.
im haya ha-Kohen tamei bamishmar she-zakha ba-korban tzibbur le-hakriv.
Oh, really? I don't, that maybe he's trying to answer my question,
but I don't think that's the
scenario... but let's keep on reading because it's going to be asking
the same questions. Who do you assign it to? Who gets to
eat the meat? The only idea of assigning and rights to eat
the meat only applies when you're bringing your private thing to the
בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash, Maybe it's a lottery or something that... I know, it's
what Steinsaltz says.
I know, it's what Steinsaltz says, but I don't know if it's
true. But okay, let's read it and then we can discuss it
more. Okay. אם היה כהן טמא בקרבן ציבור. im haya Kohen tamei
be-korban tzibbur. So he was a כהן טמא Kohen tamei and it
was a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. What does רש"י Rashi say? Maybe
רש"י Rashi. doesn't say anything. No, look at
רש"י. Rashi אם היה הכהן. im haya ha-Kohen. Oh, רש"י Rashi says
של המשמר שטמא ויש לו קרבן ציבור להקריב. shel ha-mishmar she-tamei ve-yesh
lo korban tzibbur le-hakriv. So maybe that's what you're telling me that
he's reading it. It's not you're bringing it not your משמר, mishmar,
right. So okay, I, I, I ask מחילה mechila from Steinsaltz. He's
just saying what רש"י Rashi. says. But I still don't exactly, but
I... so he's obviously dealing with the problem of the קרבן ציבור,
korban tzibbur, but then I don't understand... let's keep on reading because
then I don't understand the question. Okay. אם היה כהן טמא בקרבן
ציבור. im haya Kohen tamei be-korban tzibbur. You're כהן טמא Kohen tamei
and it's your קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur to bring. I don't know
how it became your קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur to bring, you're a
כהן טמא. Kohen tamei. Anyway, let's keep on reading. נותנו לכל מי
שירצה. nosno le-khol mi she-yirtzeh. You give it to whichever כהן kohen
you
want. ועבודתו ועורו לאנשי משמר. ve-avodasav ve-oro le-anshei mishmar. So you still
have the right to be מקריב makriv, it, so you still get
the right to assign it. But everybody gets to eat it because
the הלכה halacha is that a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur that's brought
בטומאה be-tuma is brought בטומאה be-tuma but it's not eaten בטומאה. be-tuma.
So therefore even though you're טמא, tamei, since it's a קרבן ציבור
korban tzibbur you have a right to bring it, so since you
have a right to bring it you have a right to assign
it. But since it's not eaten בטומאה, be-tuma, so you didn't have
a right to eat it, so therefore you don't have a right
to assign who gets to eat the meat and it's eaten equally
by everybody.
It shouldn't be eaten בטומאה be-tuma unless everyone is טמא. tamei.
No, even if everybody's טמא, tamei, it's not eaten בטומאה. be-tuma.
So what happens to it, it gets burned?
Yeah. Okay.
Now. היכי דמי? Heikhi dami? What's the case? אי דאיכא טהורים, I
de-ika tehorim, if there are טהור tahor כהנים Kohanim around, טמאי מי
מצו עבדו? tamei mi matzu avdu? How did you start with having
a right to bring it? What do you mean you're... oh, it's
a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur and you're a כהן טמא Kohen tamei
but it was your right to bring it. What do you mean
it was your right to bring it? You're טמא. tamei. טהורים tehorim
are supposed to bring. ואי, Ve-i, let's keep on reading, ואי דליכא
טהורים, ve-i de-leka tehorim, if everybody is טמא, tamei, so they have,
everybody is טמא, tamei, כהן טמא Kohen tamei has to bring it,
so they assigned it to you, so ועבודתו ועורו לאנשי משמר, ve-avodasav
ve-oro le-anshei mishmar, so what do you mean that everybody get... so
fine, so you gave it to another כהן, kohen they're all טמאים,
teme'im, you can do it, anybody can do it, you gave it
to another one, but they... but everybody else gets to eat it.
What do you mean everybody else gets to eat it? If they're
all טמא, tamei, nobody gets to eat it. Okay. So הא טמאים
נינהו. ha teme'im ninhu. They're all טמאים. teme'im. So what's the case
that you could bring it even though you're טמא, tamei, so that
would require that everybody else would be טמא? tamei? So what would
be the case you could bring it and you can't eat it
but they
can? ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, אימא לבעלי מומים טהורים שבאותו משמר. Eima
l'ba'alei mumim tehorim sheba'oto mishmar. Fine.
All the כהנים Kohanim. who are not בעלי מום Ba'alei mum are
טמאים. tme'im. So it's going to be brought by טמא. tamei. טומאה
Tumah gets overridden for קרבן ציבור. Korban tzibur. בעל מום Ba'al mum
doesn't get overridden. So the קרבן korban has to be brought by
one of the כהנים טמאים. Kohanim tme'im. You're one of the כהנים
טמאים, Kohanim tme'im, you could bring it. For whatever reason, you're choosing
not to, so you give it to another כהן טמא. Kohen tamei.
Okay, but now who gets to eat it? None of the טמאים
tme'im can eat it. Ironically, the טמאים tme'im could be מקריב, makriv
but you know who gets to eat it? The בעלי מומים Ba'alei
mumim who are טהור. tahor. Okay, they can't be מקריב, makriv but
because they're טהור tahor they get to eat it. So you can
assign it to another כהן kohen and it gets eaten by the
בעלי מומים Ba'alei mumim who are טהור. tahor. Okay. Anyway, so I
see that, you know, רש״י Rashi does explain this, that you were
the כהן kohen who's טמא, tamei, but I don't understand it. It's
time to bring a מוסף. Musaf. We're all טמאים. tme'im. We give
it there to Michael to bring it. Okay. Since when do we
have a הלכה halacha that in not the scenario of you coming
and bringing your private קרבן, korban, that of us in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash assigning it, that now Michael has some particular rights
that he can now assign over to somebody else? And even if
that's somehow true in the הקרבה, hakravah, it is certainly not true
in the אכילה. achilah. The אכילה achilah is always shared equally by
the כהנים Kohanim regardless of who was
מקריב makriv it. So I just don't understand this scenario in the
גמרא Gemara where it assumes you had some right of אכילה achilah
that you were, I don't know what's going on. Anyway, moving on.
Okay. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Okay, we just said. אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, אם היה כהן גדול אונן. im hayah Kohen Gadol
onen. Now let's say it was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who
was an אונן, onen, and he decided that today of all days
was the day that he was going to bring a קרבן. korban.
Okay. Now the הלכה halacha is a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who's
an אונן, onen, it says מן המקדש לא יצא ולא יחלל את
מקדש אלהיו. min haMikdash lo yetzei v'lo yechalel es Mikdash Elokav. Even
if a relative died, he continues to do the עבודה, avodah but
he doesn't eat the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. He does the עבודה, he
doesn't eat it. So he on the day that he is an
אונן, onen, that a relative just died, he's coming to bring a
קרבן. korban, If it's voluntary, he
could. Right,
right. So you just do the minimum, this is a קרבן ציבור.
Korban tzibur.
Yeah, we don't say that. He could be מקריב makriv, it, but
he can't eat it. So it's similar to the scenario before, like
the כהן who was like a זקן zaken or something. You know,
you could be מקריב makriv. it so you get to assign who
else could be מקריב, makriv, but because you're not allowed to eat,
so you don't get to assign
that. אם היה כהן גדול אונן, im hayah Kohen Gadol onen, נותנו
לכל כהן שירצה ועבודתו ובשרו לאנשי משמר. nosno l'chol kohen sheyirtzeh va'avodaso
u'vesaro l'anshei mishmar. You give it to whichever כהן you want, but
the meat gets eaten by everybody because you don't have a right
to eat it. מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? What's he telling
us? תנינא, Tanina, we taught, כהן גדול מקריב אונן ואינו אוכל. Kohen
Gadol makriv onen v'eino ochel. He's
מקריב אונן makriv onen but he doesn't eat the קרבנות korbanot as
an אונן. onen. ואינו חולק לאכול בערב. V'eino cholek l'echol ba'erev. Not
only that, he doesn't have a right to a portion of the
קרבן korban that he should be able to eat it in the
evening when his אנינות aninus is over. Okay, so clearly he's out
of the פרשה parsha when it comes to אכילה, achilah, but he
still can be מקריב. makriv So of course he can assign the
הקרבה hakravah but he can't assign the אכילה. achilah. So the גמרא
gemara. says no. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Sal'ka da'atach amina, I would have
thought כי חס רחמנא עליה דכהן גדול לקרובי הוא. ki chas Rachmana
aleih d'Kohen Gadol l'kruvei hu. When did the תורה Torah say okay
you know what even though you're an אונן onen you could still
be מקריב, makriv that's to מקריב yourself. It's an interesting phrase, חס
רחמנא, chas Rachmana, the תורה Torah has רחמנות rachmanus on him. I
think a lot of people think it's the opposite of having רחמנות
rachmanus on him, it's forcing him to stay in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash, not letting him take care of his מת. meis. But
anyway, meaning, but it's not a privilege that can be assigned. It's
a special thing that if you yourself are doing the הקרבה hakravah
as an אונן onen it's going to be allowed. אבל לשוויי שליח
הוא עצמו לא עביד הקרבה. aval l'shavei shaliach hu atzmo lo avid
hakravah. Once you yourself are not doing the הקרבה, hakravah, it's not
some right that you can assign to somebody else. So לא מצי
משוי, lo matzi mashvei, he can't do, קמשמע לן kamashma lan that
he can. Once he's entitled to do it, he can assign that
right. Okay. So that is the end of the digression that when
a כהן brings his own קרבן korban he's entitled to do the
עבודה and to have the meat. Moving on. Okay.
Now back to the case that we've been dealing with in anticipation.
הגוזל את הגר ונשבע לו ומת. Hagozel es hager v'nishba lo u'meis.
Somebody steals from a גר ger and swears to him and dies.
הרי זה משלם קרן וחומש. Harei zeh meshalem keren v'chomesh. So again
he pays the קרן keren and the חומש. chomesh. But who this
time? לכהנים. l'Kohanim. ואשם למזבח. V'asham l'mizbe'ach.
And the אשם asham. of course goes to the altar like it
always does. שנאמר ואם אין לאיש גואל להשיב האשם אליו. Shene'emar v'im
ein la'ish go'el l'hashiv ha'asham eilav.
If the person has no redeemer to whom you can return the
אשם, asham and the אשם asham? here means the principal. האשם המושב
לה' לכהן. Ha'asham hamushav la'Hashem l'Kohen.
The אשם asham that is returned to God goes to the כהן.
מלבד איל הכפורים
in addition to the ram of atonement which is what we would
call the אשם. asham, אשר יכפר בו עליו Asher yechaper bo alav
which he would use to atone. Okay. היה מעלה
את הכסף ואת האשם. Hayah ma'aleh es hakesef v'es ha'asham. Now you
were bringing the money and the אשם. asham Again now אשם asham,
in this means the קרבן korban. אשם. asham Anyway it was the
case of גזל הגר, gezel ha-ger the גר ger died etc. he
was bringing the whole thing to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, ומת.
U'meis. And the guy who was now bringing it to the בית
המקדש died. Now remember there's two things going on here. There's a
כפרה. kaparah. You don't do כפרה kaparah for a guy after he's
dead, you don't bring a קרבן korban. for a guy after he's
dead. But then there's the question about the money. So here's an
important question: the money that is going to the כהנים, Kohanim
how much is that part of the כפרה? kapara? Right? If a
guy had an obligation to return to -- to a normal person,
the principal and the fifth, and to bring a קרבן, korban. and
he died, you wouldn't bring the קרבן korban after his death, but
presumably you would return at least the principal. The fifth would be
an interesting question. Is the fifth like a כפרה kapara and that's
only when the guy is alive or would you give it even
-- but certainly you'd return the principal to the נגזל. nigzal. In
this case, you're giving everything to the כהנים. Kohanim And when you're
giving it to the כהנים, kohanim the פסוק says להשם לכהן. L'Hashem
L'Kohein, So it's very easy to look at all of this, even
the principal, as a type of a קרבן, korban, as a type
of a כפרה. kapara. So if the guy is dead, do the
heirs have to give the principal to the כהנים? kohanim It's a
good question, right? So let's see what it says. So it says
ומת, u-mais, הכסף ינתן לבניו. hakesef yinasein l'banav. No, you do not
have to give the principal to the כהנים. kohanim, The sons get
to keep the money. ואשם, v'asham, now how about the אשם? asham,
So what's the הלכה halacha of a קרבן korban, of a חטאת
chatas or an אשם asham after the owner dies? So if it's
a חטאת, chatas, you let the animal die. If it's an אשם,
asham ירעה עד שיסתאב, yireh ad she-yista-eiv, you let it graze until
it gets a blemish, וימכר, v'yimacheir, and then you sell it, ויפלו
דמיו לנדבה, v'yiplu damav l'nedava, and the proceeds go to bring a
קרבן עולה, korban olah, which is a type of a קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibbur. Okay, so that's the normal הלכה halacha of an אשם
asham that the owner dies. The חידוש chiddush is that the money
is not looked at as a type of a קרבן, korban. even
though it says להשם לכהן, even though it's going to the בית
המקדש, it's going to the כהנים, kohanim it's basically looked at as
a monetary obligation, and therefore if the guy dies, the kids get
to keep it. And presumably that's true about the fifth as well.
You know, you would think maybe the fifth is thought of as
a special type of a כפרה. kapara. No, that all gets to
be kept by the kids. Yes, דב? Dov?
Wouldn't it be possible to say it still goes to the בית
המקדש but not as a כפרה kapara but as a -- as
a גבאי? gabbai?
Yeah, it would, and that's the חידוש, chiddush, that it's not. That
we see this as a --
wait a minute, did I misstate this? I know -- no, I
think I misstated it. It's the opposite. Wait.
It's the opposite. I'm sorry, I'm sorry. I mean, I said the
הלכה halacha right, but I think I explained the logic in the
wrong
way.
If we were to be viewing this as a monetary obligation with
the כהנים kohanim. taking the place of the גר, ger, then even
after the guy died, the money should be going to the כהנים.
kohanim Because let's say the guy died, let's say it was a
case about just a simple case of a נגזל, nigzal, like not
a גר, ger, or whatever. You know, the guy died, the principal
would go to the נגזל, nigzal, right? It's still money that's owed
to the נגזל. nigzal. So the fact that -- I said it
the wrong way, excuse me. The fact that you do not give
the money to the כהנים kohanim, after the guy died means you
are viewing it -- yeah, I said it the wrong way --
you are viewing it as a type of a קרבן. korban? So
the same way you don't bring a קרבן, korban, you don't do
any כפרה kapara act after the guy is dead, so the same
way you're not going to bring a קרבן korban, after the guy
is dead, you're not going to give the money after the guy
is dead, and the kids get to keep the money. Okay, right.
Everybody gets this? I sort of said it the wrong way. If
you were to view this just as a debt, if the guy
died without it being a case of the גר, ger, the guy
died, okay, what would you do? You wouldn't bring a קרבן korban,
after his death, but what would you do with the גזילה gezeila
that he had under his possession? You'd give it back to the
נגזל. nigzal. Right? Everybody with me? So in this case, if the
כהנים kohanim are just seen as the assigned heirs of the גר,
ger, then after the guy died you should give them the money.
But it seems like it's saying they're not. It seems like the
giving of the money in this case when the guy isn't around
is part of an act of כפרה. kapara. And therefore, since the
guy isn't around and there's no כפרה kapara to be done, the
kids get to keep the money. All right, so I think --
I'm so -- so the הלכה halacha is right but I explained
it the wrong way. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like
this. No, let's look at one minute -- let me just look
at רש"י. Rashi,
Yeah, look at רש"י, Rashi that's what רש"י Rashi says. הכסף ינתן
לבניו, Hakesef yinasein l'banav, רש"י says, שגזלו, she-gazlo, דזכה ביה מיתת הגר,
d'zacha bei meesas hager, from a monetary perspective it was his. אלא
דבעי למעבד השבה, Ella d'ba-ei l'me-evad hashavah, כי היכי דתהוי ליה כפרה,
ki heichi d'tehavi leih kapara, but it was required as part of
an act of -- of a כפרה. kapara. והשתא תו ליכא כפרה
כיון דמית ליה. V'hashta tu leika kapara keivan d'mais leih. Now there's
no longer a כפרה kapara because he's dead. Okay? So since --
so if it was a monetary obligation you would have to do
it, but now it's just a כפרה kapara obligation and he doesn't.
So I think an interesting question to ask would be in not
in the case of the גר, ger, but a normal case, the
guy died, okay, the נגזל's nigzal still around or the נגזל's nigzal
estate is still around. You have to give back the principal because
that's a monetary obligation. What's the story about
the חומש? chomesh? If the חומש chomesh is part of the כפרה,
kapara, then maybe you wouldn't have to give the חומש chomesh to
the נגזל. nigzal. Okay, so here's -- okay, so now we continue.
Okay, נתן הכסף לאנשי משמר ומת. Nasan hakesef l'anshei mishmar u-mais. Now
let's say he -- the guy gave the money to the כהנים
kohanim. and then he died. So now the heirs are going to
come and say, "Look, our father died. He didn't get a chance
to bring -- "" Now let's say the guy gave the money
to the כהנים kohanim and then he died. So now the יורשים
yorshim are going to come and say, look, our father died, he
didn't get a chance to bring his קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, so
he didn't get to finish his כפרה. kapparah. So since his כפרה
kapparah never really got to be finished, so give us back the
money. Okay. אין היורשים יכולים להוציא מידם. Ein hayorshim yecholim lehotzi miyadam.
No, they can't get the money back, שנאמר ואיש אשר יתן לכהן
לו יהיה, shene'emar v'ish asher yitein lakohain lo yiyeh, learning from this
other פסוק that's written in that context. Once the כהן gets it,
he gets rights to it. So even though we've established that in
this case the money is part of the כפרה kapparah and the
guy dies before he fully achieved the כפרה, kapparah, once it's given
to the כהנים they keep
it. נתן הכסף ליהויריב ואשם לידעיה. Natan hakesef l'Yehoyariv v'asham l'Yedaya. Now,
let's say you gave the money, what order does it matter what
order you do these various acts of כפרה? kapparah? There's the money
and there's the קרבן. korban So יהויריב Yehoyariv was the first משמר
mishmar and ידעיה Yedaya was the second. It basically means you first
gave the money and then a week later you brought the קרבן.
korban. יצא, Yatza, you're
יצא. yotzei. Now אשם ליהויריב asham l'Yehoyariv because it says אשם המושב
להשם לכהן מלבד איל הכיפורים, asham hamushav l'Hashem lakohain milvad ayil hakippurim,
so it sounds like it's first the money and then the קרבן.
korban, However, let's say it's אשם ליהויריב, asham l'Yehoyariv, first you gave
the אשם, asham הכסף לידעיה, hakesef l'Yedaya, and then you gave the
כסף kesef the next week, אם קיים האשם, im kayam ha'asham, if
the קרבן korban, is still around, they didn't actually מקריב it, it's,
you know,
it's online to be brought, יקריבוהו בני ידעיה, yakrivuhu b'nei Yedaya, then
bring it as brought after the money you're יצא. yotzei. ואם לאו,
V'im lav, but if not, then you weren't יצא yotzei when the
אשם asham? was brought before the money was given back. You first
have to, you know what it's like? You have to sort of
like you have to get the guy do מחילה mechila from the
person you injured before then you do תשובה tshuva for God. Okay.
ויחזיר ויביא אשם אחר. V'yachazir v'yavi asham acher. שהמביא גזילו עד שלא
הביא אשמו, Shehameivi gezeilo ad shelo heivi ashamo, if you bring, if
you return the גזילה gezeilah before the אשם, asham, יצא, yatza, and
then you bring the אשם asham. a while later you're יצא. yotzei.
הביא אשמו עד שלא הביא גזילו, Heivi ashamo ad shelo heivi gezeilo,
if you brought the אשם asham before the money, לא יצא. lo
yatza. Now it's not exactly clear because it makes it like it
was different weeks. Let's say you came the same day and you
gave it to the כהנים, said here's the money, here's the קרבן,
korban and you walked away. And the כהנים it took them, well,
I guess if you gave them the money right away they already
had the money. I'm trying to think of a scenario when you
sort of did it the same time but they made the order
like a different order. Okay, but anyway. נתן את הקרן ולא נתן
את החומש. Natan et hakeren v'lo natan et hachomesh. If you gave
the קרן keren and not the חומש, chomesh, אין החומש מעכב. ein
hachomesh m'akev. If you gave the principal and not the fifth, the
principal is, the fifth is not מעכב, m'akev, you still have your
כפרה, kapparah, although of course you're supposed to give your fifth. So
what this משנה mishna establishes besides the order of the money and
then the קרבן, korban you know, what this משנה mishna establishes is
the idea that the money, at least in the case of the
גזל הגר, gezel ha-ger, right, the money is a necessary part of
כפרה kapparah and therefore, and only in the case of a גזל
הגר, gezel ha-ger? we always assume it's part of a כפרה, kapparah,
that's what we were talking about yesterday, that there could be a
מצות השבה mitzvat hashavah even if there's no monetary obligation, but in
the case of גזל הגר gezel ha-ger, it's only part of the
כפרה kapparah and it's not a monetary obligation. So therefore if it's
only a part of the כפרה kapparah and the guy is dead,
the kids get to keep it. All right, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. אשם זה קרן. Asham
zeh keren. It says אשם המושב להשם לכהן, asham hamushav l'Hashem lakohain,
so in this context אשם asham. means the principal. המושב זה חומש,
Hamushav zeh chomesh, that's the fifth. And then it says in addition
to the איל הכיפורים ayil hakippurim which is the קרבן. korban או
אינו אלא אשם זה איל, O eino ela asham zeh ayil, maybe
the אשם asham. means the ram, the קרבן? korban, ולמאי נפקא מינה
לאפוקי מדרבא. Ul'mai nafka mina l'afukei mid'Rava. Now what difference does it
make? What is the halachic significance of the fact that the תורה
Torah is labeling the principal, the money, an אשם? asham. So one
of the points is what we just said, that it's just about
כפרה kapparah and if the guy's dead you get to keep it.
Okay, it's not about any monetary obligation to the כהנים. Okay, but
there's another point that's important, like רבא Rava says. דאמר רבא, D'amar
Rava, גזל הגר שהחזירו בלילה לא יצא. gezel hager shehechziro balaila lo
yatza. Because we're treating the money here as a type of a
קרבן, korban a type of an אשם, asham it has to follow
the same הלכה halacha of the קרבנות. korbanot. So let's say you
gave it to the כהנים at nighttime. You didn't fulfill your obligation
of giving the money back because it has to be like a
קרבן, korban. it has to be given during the day. החזירו חציו
לא יצא, Hechziro chetzyo lo yatza, if you gave half today and
half tomorrow. מאי טעמא אשם קריה רחמנא, Mai ta'ama asham kariya Rachmana,
so the תורה called it an אשם. asham Now what's say you
gave it to a כהן outside the בית המקדש, right? Even if
it was a כהן who was, it was his משמר. mishmar. Okay,
but you gave, maybe that you're also not יצא. yotzei. So very
interesting, the money gets treated as a type of a קרבן, an
act of, yes. Now the interesting question I'd like to ask is,
well, forget it. Okay, so that's, I was going to say, what
about the case of when it's not a גזל הגר? So when
it's not a גזל הגר, it might be a necessary part of
כפרה. kapparah. I'm not entitled to bring my קרבן until I return
David the money I stole from you. So it's a necessary part
of כפרה, kapparah, but it's not like a קרבן. You're not a
כהן and this transaction is not taking place in the בית המקדש,
right? So in the normal case, it like must get taken place
of first before the כפרה. kapparah. But in the גזל הגר where
it's given to the כהנים, it actually is a type of a
קרבן, an act of, yes.
So if you're not יצא yotzei then you force them to give
it back to you or do you say, oh no? No, the
משנה, mishna, what do you mean?
Oh, no, then I can give.
And they just do it again the next day?
Yeah. Okay. כשהוא אומר *kshehu omer*, okay, so אשם כעיקר רחמנא *asham
k'ikar rachmana*. כשהוא אומר מלבד איל הכיפורים *kshehu omer milvad eil hakippurim*,
הוי אומר *havei omer*, so because it says in addition to the
to the קרבן *korban*, אשם זה קרן *asham ze keren*, we know
it's a קרן *keren* and now the גמרא *gemara* says there's a
very important significance that in the case of גזל הגר *gezel hager*
where it's given to the כהנים *kohanim*, the money actually has a
status like a קרבן *korban*. תניא אידך *tanya idach*, we've done another
ברייתא *braisa*. אשם זה קרן *asham ze keren*. המושב זה חומש *hamushav
ze chomesh*. או אינו אלא אשם זה חומש *o eino ela asham
ze chomesh*, maybe, okay, we know that it's not talking about the
קרבן *korban*. איל הכיפורים *eil hakippurim* is a קרבן *korban*, but maybe
the word אשם *asham* means the fifth, which might make sense cause
that's like the extra thing that's being added on. למאי נפקא מינה
לאפוקי ממתניתין *lemai nafka mina lafukei mi-matnisin* to reject our משנה *mishna*?
Now, what did our משנה *mishna* say? נתן לו את הקרן ולא
נתן את החומש אין החומש מעכב *nasan lo es hakeren velo nasan
es hachomesh ein hachomesh me'akeiv*. Our משנה *mishna* says the key for
the כפרה kapara *kapara* is the
principle. אדרבה *adderaba*, let me say the opposite. חומש מעכב *chomesh me'akeiv*,
maybe the אשם *asham* means the חומש *chomesh*. Right? I think it
has a lot of סברא *sevara* to say that. That's the extra
thing. That's not just paying back. Maybe that's the real קרבן *korban*
כפרה *kapara*. כשהוא אומר והשיב את אשמו בראשו וחמישיתו יוסף עליו *kshehu
omer veheshiv es ashamo berosho vachamishiso yosef alav*, return the אשם *asham*
at the head and then add a fifth. So then clearly the
אשם *asham* isn't the fifth. הוי אומר אשם זה קרן *havei omer
asham ze keren*. אשם *asham* is clearly the principle. So we know
that it's the principle cause everything else is excluded in the פסוק
*pasuk* and because of that we learned that the principle in the
case of גזל הגר *gezel hager* has a status like a קרבן
*korban*. תניא אידך *tanya idach*, we've done another ברייתא *braisa*. אשם זה
קרן *asham ze keren*. המושב זה חומש *hamushav ze chomesh*. Okay. ובגזל
הגר הכתוב מדבר *ub'gezel hager hakesuv medaber*. או אינו אלא המושב זה
כפל *o eino ela hamushav ze kefel* ובגניבת הגר הכתוב מדבר *ubig'neivas
hager hakesuv medaber*. How do you know המושב *hamushav* is talking about
the fifth? Maybe המושב *hamushav* is כפל *kefel* and maybe it's talking
about if you did a גניבה *gneiva* from a גר ger, *ger*.
You pay the double to the כהנים *kohanim*, which is not true.
If you did a גניבה *gneiva* from a גר *ger* and you
didn't have this case of the שבועה *shvua* or whatever, you know,
you keep it. כשהוא אומר והשיב את אשמו בראשו וחמישיתו *kshehu omer
veheshiv es ashamo berosho vachamishiso*,
so clearly we're not talking about גניבה *gneiva*. We're talking about a
fifth. הרי ממון המשתלם בראש *harei mamon hamishtaleim berosh*. So you see
that the cases that we're talking about the principle and not a
case of a doubling of the principle. הכתוב מדבר *hakesuv medaber*. Okay.
גופא *gufa*. אמר רבא Rava *amar Rava*. גזל הגר שהחזירו בלילה לא
יצא *gezel hager shehecheziru balayla lo yatza*. So if you return the
principle at night, לא יצא *lo yatza*. You weren't יוצא *yotzei*. החזירו
חציו *hecheziru chetzyon*, we just said that. לא יצא *lo yatza*. It's
a type of a קרבן *korban*. Okay. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? *mai
ta'ama*? אשם קריה רחמנא *asham kayei rachmana*. The Torah calls it an
אשם *asham*. ואמר רבא Rava *ve'amar Rava*, Rava also said, גזל הגר
שאין בו שוה פרוטה לכל כהן וכהן לא יצא *gezel hager she'ein
bo shaveh pruta lechol kohein vekohein lo yatza*. Now this is really
difficult, right? Cause if it's not a פרוטה *pruta* to go equally
to every כהן *kohein* in that משמר mishmar. *mishmar*, you weren't יוצא
*yotzei*. לא יצא ידי חובתו *lo yatza yedei chovaso*. There's nothing you
can do about that. So, right? So in that case what do
you do? You never get כפרה *kapara*? You still, you stole a
dollar from a גר *ger* and there are fifty כהנים *kohanim*, and
what are you supposed to do? You're not going to get כפרה
*kapara*. מאי טעמא דכתיב האשם המושב עד שיהא אשם לכל כהן וכהן
*mai ta'ama dichsiv ha'asham hamushav ad sheyehei asham lechol kohein vekohein*. Until
every כהן *kohein* gets a little bit. Since we learned out before
that it gets equally distributed. I don't know why you don't look
at them as a corporate entity and you're returning it to the
body of the כהנים *kohanim* and I don't know what you're supposed
to do in that case. So in that case you're just stuck?
Okay, find some other גר *ger* and steal more from him so
that you can return it. I don't... okay. Yeah, right. In the
גמרא *gemara* hit a guy or whatever, say hit him another time,
whatever. Okay. Exactly. Anyway, so that's a strange דרשה *drasha*. בעי רבא
Ba'ei Rava. *ba'ei Rava*. אינו ממשמרת שהוא יהויריב ויש בו למשמרת ידעיה
Yidaya *eino mimishmeres shehu Yehoyariv veyesh bo lemishmeres Yedaya*. So you basically
came to return the money and it was יהויריב *Yehoyariv*'s week. And
they had a big משמר *mishmar*. And if you were to divide
it equally, they wouldn't each get a פרוטה *pruta*. But in next
week it's going to be ידעיה Yidaya *Yedaya*'s משמר *mishmar* and it's
a smaller משמר *mishmar* and everybody would get a פרוטה *pruta*. מהו
*mahu*? Are you יוצא *yotzei* your מצות השבה *mitzvas hashavah*? So גמרא
*gemara* says היכי דמי *heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא דיהביה לידעיה
במשמרת ידעיה Yidaya, *ileima d'yahvei l'Yedaya b'mishmeres Yedaya*? If you waited a
week and gave it all to ידעיה Yidaya *Yedaya*? הא איתפי *ha
itpei*?
So everybody got a שוה פרוטה *shaveh pruta*, of course you're יוצא
*yotzei*. No. לא צריכא דיהביה לידעיה במשמרתא דיהויריב *lo tzricha d'yahvei l'Yedaya
b'mishmarta d'Yehoyariv*. That you came week number one. It was יהויריב *Yehoyariv*'s
week. But you looked and you saw not everybody's going to get
a שוה פרוטה *shaveh pruta*. I'm not going to be יוצא *yotzei*.
So you, you know, turned to your, I don't know, friend who
was from the משמר *mishmar* of ידעיה *Yedaya*. And you said, here
buddy, here's the money, split it amongst amongst you the rest of
the משמר *mishmar*, you know, next week when it's your when it's
your turn. Okay. So do we say that that's good because anyway
since
since since what is it? Since...
exactly. So do we say since יהויריב *Yehoyariv* didn't have any rights
to it because you couldn't be יוצא *yotzei* with יהויריב *Yehoyariv*, essentially
the right to collect it passed on to ידעיה *Yedaya*. Okay. Now
of course you have to give the money back before you bring
the קרבן *korban*. So the point is that you gave it now
to ידעיה *Yedaya*, it's not yet their week, and יהויריב *Yehoyariv* is
going to be bringing the קרבן *korban*, but that should count like
you gave already have given the money. Okay. דיהביה לידעיה במשמרתא דיהויריב
מאי *deyahvei l'Yedaya b'mishmarta d'Yehoyariv mai*?
What do we say? מי אמרינן כיון דלאו משמרתא הוא ולאו כלום
הוא *mi amrinan keivan d'lav mishmarta hu velo klum hu*? It's not
their משמרתא *mishmarta*, so it's not a good השבה *hashavah* especially since
we called it like an... אשם and a קרבן, how can you
bring an אשם and a קרבן if they're not working this week?
או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say כיון דלא חזי ליה
נקרא לידעיה, keivan d'lo chazi leh nikrah l'Yidaya, since ידעיה has no
rights to it? So because it's going to... ידעיה goes anyway, going
to ידעיה, so even though you give it to ידעיה the week
before, it counts as a good act of returning the money. תיקו.
Teyku. Yes, Charlie.
רבא Rava lived hundreds of years after they destroyed the temple and
they still remembered which were the large...
oh, that's... oh, which were the... I don't know if they remembered
which were the large ones, I think they're just giving it as
a hypothetical. בעי רבא. רבא asked: כהנים שיחלקו גזל הגר כנגד גזל
הגר. kohanim sheyichalku gezel ha-ger k'neged gezel ha-ger. So this was a
very good week for the כהנים of this משמר. A lot of
people came to return גזל הגר this week, okay? And therefore, so
now here's the question: So one guy gave back 1,000, one guy
back 50, etc. Now, here's the point. Can we just say, let's
just total up the total amount we got in גזל הגר, you
know, and then just divide it equally, right? Put it all in
one pot like, you know, we collect our tips at the end
of the day and then we divide it equally. Okay, can we
do that? Or do we have to say like by any קרבן
you can't say by the קרבנות, korbanot, let's just put all the
קרבנות korbanot together, all the meat, and everybody gets, you know, x
amount. Okay, no. Every קרבן has to be divided individually amongst the
כהנים. Do we say the same about גזל הגר? Or do we
say like money is fungible? Or do we say that since we're
treating the money as a קרבן, each unit of money has to
get divided. Okay. מהו שיחלקו גזל הגר כנגד גזל הגר. mahu sheyichalku
gezel ha-ger k'neged gezel ha-ger. Can we say, I'll take this גזל
הגר, you take that one, or do we have to divide each
one equally? מי אמרינן אשם קרא רחמנא, mi amrinan asham kara rachmana,
it's called an אשם. מה אשם אין חולקין אשם כנגד אשם, mah
asham ein chalkin asham k'neged asham, you can't just put them all
in one pile and divide them, you have to divide each one.
אף גזל הגר אין חולקין גזל הגר כנגד גזל הגר. af gezel
ha-ger ein chalkin gezel ha-ger k'neged gezel ha-ger. או דלמא, O dilma,
or do we say גזל הגר ממונא הוא? gezel ha-ger mamona hu?
At the end of the day, it's still money even if it
works as a type of a קרבן and there are some הלכות
halachot about how it's given and it can't be given at night,
at the end of the day money is fungible. Okay. הדר פשטיה,
Hadar pash'ei, in the end he concluded: אשם קרא רחמנא. asham kara
rachmana. Now let's be consistent, it's called an אשם. רב אחא בריה
דרבא מתני לה בהדיא. Rav Aha brei de-Rava matni leh be-hedya. So
רבא didn't even have a question, he just taught straight. אמר רבא
כהנים אין חולקין גזל הגר כנגד גזל הגר. amar Rava kohanim ein
chalkin gezel ha-ger k'neged gezel ha-ger. מאי טעמא? אשם קרא רחמנא, asham
kara rachmana, because it is called an אשם. Okay, so I guess
we will end here. But again to repeat this is a... אשם
and because it is... just to clarify again the thing I said
before, just because it's only there's nobody the money is owed to
and we're going to explore this a little bit more tomorrow, but
the כהנים you don't owe it to them דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot,
it's only a type of a קרבן. So therefore if the guy
dies, the kids get to keep it. And as opposed to a
case where the guy is the נגזל nigzal is not a גר,
the נגזל's nigzal alive and the guy dies, the principal still has
to be returned to the נגזל. nigzal. What the גמרא has not
explored is if the guy died, does the אשם have to be
given... does the fifth have to be given to the נגזל. nigzal.
How much is the fifth a monetary obligation or how much is
it purely a type of a כפרה and therefore not necessary after
the guy has... after the גזלן gazlan is dead. That is not
explored by the גמרא but we'll continue looking at this tomorrow.